Most people think that LLMs can really
only produce text and they don't think
about the second thing they're really
good at, which is producing structured
outputs. I have here an invoice that I'm
going to pass to the LLM to extract out
the information because it's in a PDF
and I can't put a PDF in a database to
work out when the last time I bought
oranges was, for instance. I'm going to
take that invoice and read it into
memory here using Node. Then I'm going
to pass that to Claude 3.7 Sonnet. Here
I'm using the AISDK generate text and
TypeScript. Of course, now we're using
generate text here, which of course
means we're going to get a text output.
And that's fine. When I run this, I get
a nice little summary of everything in
the PDF, but instead I'm going to swap
generate text for generate object. And
I'm going to pass it a Zod schema for
the things I want to get back from my
query. I want to know all the items I
purchased in an array of name, quantity,
and price. I want to know the total
amount I spent, and I want to know the
currency. This will use the structured
outputs feature of that model if it has
it. It will convert this schema into
JSON schema to pass it to the model and
then we'll also use ZOD to validate the
thing that we get back. This means that
when we run this we get back this entire
object which is both runtime safe
because it's being validated by ZOD but
also type safe because the types are
being inferred from ZOD. Beautiful. So
structured outputs with the ASDK is
really simple and really powerful.